<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration to the Baptists concerning the name of the Lord, and what it is to be baptized thereinto, and the nature of the Lord, and what it is to be made partaker thereof : and sheweth that none can be saved, but such as are baptized into the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, into which name and nature, the apostles were sent to baptize, and not into water : shewing also, that the apostles were made the administrators of the Spirits baptism ... : also a discovery of the Baptists foundation ... / written by one who was sometimes one with them in the shadows ... but have now found the day wherein the shadows flee away, and hath received another name besides Humphry Wollrich.</title>
            <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39137</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18218834</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18218834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107205</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66855)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107205)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1138:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration to the Baptists concerning the name of the Lord, and what it is to be baptized thereinto, and the nature of the Lord, and what it is to be made partaker thereof : and sheweth that none can be saved, but such as are baptized into the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, into which name and nature, the apostles were sent to baptize, and not into water : shewing also, that the apostles were made the administrators of the Spirits baptism ... : also a discovery of the Baptists foundation ... / written by one who was sometimes one with them in the shadows ... but have now found the day wherein the shadows flee away, and hath received another name besides Humphry Wollrich.</title>
                  <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G.C. and are to be sold by Thomas Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptists --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107205:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION TO THE BAPTISTS.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Name of the Lord, and what it is to be Baptized thereinto; and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Lord, and what it is to be made partaker thereof.</p>
            <p>AND SHEWETH That none can be ſaved, but ſuch as are Baptized into the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, into which Name and Nature, the Apoſtles were ſent to Baptize; and not into Water.</p>
            <p>Shewing alſo, That the Apoſtles were made the Adminiſtrators of the Spirits Baptiſm by vertue of their Commiſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>Go ye therefore into all Nations teaching them, and Baptiſing them in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO A Diſcovery of the BAPTISTS Foundation and Bottom, and many of their principal Doctrines ſet down herein; held forth at a Diſpute in <hi>Leiceſter</hi>-Shire, at one <hi>Henry Smiths,</hi> at <hi>Wythcock,</hi> the 27 day of teh 12th. moneth, 1658. Before a multitude of people; with an Anſwer thereunto, wherein is ſhewed alſo, that the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> are ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up Types and Shadows above Chriſt, and viſible carnal created things above the inviſible, Eternal and unchangeable God.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zach. 10.12.</hi>
               </bibl> And they ſhall walk up and down in the Name of the Lord.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 12.</hi>
               </bibl> For by one Spirit are we all Baptized into one Body.</q>
            <p>Written by one who was ſometimes one with them in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, feeding upon the wind, and eating that which died of its ſelf, and did not ſatisfie; But have now found the day wherein the ſhadows flee away, and hath received another name Beſides HUMPHRY WOLLRICH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. C.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Simmons.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:107205:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107205:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Baptiſts, concerning the name of the Lord, <hi>Mat. 28.18, 19, 20.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riends, all ye that are called Baptiſts, you are they amongſt whom I have ſometime had my converſation, and as you are now, ſo was I whilſt I was among you, profeſſing a God, and a Chriſt, whom I knew not but by the hearing of the ear; and then I was looking at things that were ſeen, as you are building my foundation upon carnal, created viſible things, which all muſt periſh in the uſing, but my ſelf knew not Chriſt the Rock of Ages, who is inviſible, and eternal, and a foundation of many generations, and the foundation of his people in all generations, him have I found, whom <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets wrote of; and therefore I leave thoſe things which muſt decreaſe, as <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciples did, and follow him who muſt and doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, even Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the World, who hath lighted every man that cometh into the World, who is the end of all ſhaddowes, types, and figures the end of the Law to his people, who are come in to him, who was before ſin and tranſgreſſion was, the ſame it is that doth put an end to ſin, and finiſh tranſgreſſion, unto which, and becauſe of which the Law was added, untill the ſeed came which is made under the Law, ſhadowes, types, and figures; I ſay when he is come and doth reign and rule in his Saints; and hath condemed in them all iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin, to ſuch, and none but ſuch is Chriſt the end of the Law; for the Law takes hold of a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107205:3"/>man ſo long as he lives in ſin, for the Law was added be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſin, and none are under grace, till the Law hath condemned ſin; therefore all friends who are breathing after the Lord, but your minds ſtill without, and ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alienated from that which may be known of God in you, which is the candle of the Lord, and ſearcheth all your hearts, and tryeth all your reins, to you I ſay, let your profeſſion be what it will, and your form be what it will, it is but your own will, and ſo contrary to the will of God, you not being led into it, by the pure, eternall, unchangeable ſpirit of the Lord God, in whom as I have ſaid before, there is no variableneſs, or ſhaddow of chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; therefore in love to you all, and the welfare of your immortal ſouls, which is of more worth and value then all the World, all turn to the Light of the Lord, that ſhines in darkneſs, that convinceth you, reproves you, and checks you for all your ungodly words, and for all your hard ſpeeches, which ye have ignorantly and wickedly ſpoken againſt the Lord, and againſt his people, whom he hath anointed with the oyl of joy and gladneſſe above their brethren, who have caſt them out for his names ſake, and have ſaid, Let the Lord be glorified, as you have hated mee, and caſt mee out as an evil doer, as a blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, a heretick, and as one not fit to live upon the earth, though to this day ye can prove no evil againſt me, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in life or doctrine, but as Chriſt his Apoſtles and Saints, in all ages who were innocent, ſuffered as evil doers, by this evil and adulterous generation, who were gone a whoring from under their God, and are run into the things that are ſeen, which are temporal, and have got the ſhaddowes, types and figures, and a form, but are enemies unto, and deny the life and power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and in obedience to the Lord, becauſe of theſe things which I found among you, I turned from you, and ſeparated from you, and this is according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles doctrine, and not contrary to Scripture: But the Lord commandeth his people to ſeparate from all that walk diſorderly, under what name or form ſoever they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107205:3"/>be, and he will be a Father unto them, and a God unto them, and will dwell in them, and walk in them, and they ſhall be my ſons and daughters ſaith the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; and into this ſtate and condition, the Lord God is gathering his Sheep, which have been ſcattered in their thoughts, and imaginations, upon all the dark moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Iſrael, crying lo here, and lo there, even into a ſure reſting place, to ſit under their own vine, and under their own fig-tree, where none ſhall make them afraid, and their place of defence ſhall be the munition of rocks, where their bread is ſure, and their water given them, and they eat of the hidden Manna, which hath been hid from many generations, where they eat of the bread of life, and are refreſhed and strengthened in the Inward man, where they drink abundantly of the Rivers of pleaſures that are at the right hand of God for evermore. Into this place is the Lord God of life gathering his children more and more, even into this land which flowes with milk and honey, where they drink of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fountain, and eat of the honey out of the Rock which hath followed them in the wilderneſs, and hath led them out of darkneſs, even out of thick darkneſs; and by his Light they walk and are walking through dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and through the wilderneſs where they have been long tempted, proved and tryed, even by a way which we knew not; and he ſuffered us to hunger, and he fed us there with Manna, which had been hid from us, and by a way which we never went, hath heled us by a way which is hid from the eyes of all living, and kept cloſe from the fowls of the air; there did he lead us by the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the ſaint of the Lord; there did he lead us from one Nation to another people, and rebuked mighty Kings, yea, famous Kings for our ſakes, ſaying, Touch not mine Annointed, and do my Prophets no harm; and we have been Baptized with <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Sea, and in the Cloud, and we have heard the voice of the Lord ſpeaking out of the cloudy Pillar, and his Light is ariſen, and his arm is made Bare in us, and darkneſs is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107205:4"/>under his feet. Now he who is the Light of the world, and ſhined in the darkneſs, is riſen out of darkneſs; and in him and by him we comprehend all you who are yet in the darkneſs, in the diverſe waſhings and carnal ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which were impoſed but till the time of Reformation, and no longer; and we ſee your bottom, and know your ground, and we know your houſe of Imagery, and ſee with the eye of God, that ye are looking with beaſtly eyes, which are many in you which are in the many bodies, who are alienated and reprobated from the one body; the Light which is the Eye of God, by which his Children are led and guided into all truth, which truth ſets free from iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin, a thing which ye never look to be ſet free from in this life, but are preaching and diſputing againſt it.</p>
            <p>Therefore to you all, This is the Word of the Lord God, and a charge from the Lord God to you all that are high in your profeſſion above the Door Chriſt, Repent and turn to the Light of the Lord God in you, for there is not one of ye all that is yet come to the firſt principle, which is Repentance from dead works, for he that is dead ſinneth not; therefore come out of Babylon, out of all your inventions, imitations and likeneſſes, into which ye are run; and the Spirit of the Lord God never led you by your own Confeſſion, who ſay, the Letter is the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Guider and Teacher, which is contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, and the Scriptures, which ſay, Chriſt is given for a Covenant of Light, for a Leader, and for a Teacher of his people; therefore the leaders of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cauſeth them to Err, and they that are led of them are deſtroyed; But they that are the ſons of God, are led by the Spirit of God, and are Redeemed out of all your types, and figures, and ſhadowes, and divers waſhings; for which you have nothing to ſay or prove them by, but by the Hand-writing which we know he hath taken away, and aboliſhed, and nailed to his Croſs, which are a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Good things to come, But the Body is Chriſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which body by one Spirit we are all Baptized, whether
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107205:4"/>Jewes or Greeks, Bond or Free, and have all been made to drink into that one Spirit, in which Spirit is found the life of all types, ſhadows, and figures, and in whom there is no variableneſs, nor ſhadow of changing, and him we witneſs in us to be greater then he that is in the world; he himſelf is not of this world, but he leadeth all that follow him out of the world which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away, and gives us an entrance, and by him an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance is miniſtred into the Kingdom of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt; and this is the Saviour of the Soul, even the ingrafted word of the Lord, which ye that ſay ye are wiſe, have rejected and caſt his Law behind your backs, and to you all he is become a ſtone of ſtumbling, and Rock of offence, and the preaching of his Croſs is to you fooliſhneſs, who gird your ſelves, and eſteemed by you in that wiſdom nothing but confuſion, babling and non-ſence, though unto us that are ſaved, the power of God, and the wiſdom of God. Therefore in the fear of the Lord God, and in the dread of the Lord God, I charge you all again, Repent whilſt wiſdom uttereth her voice in the ſtreets, ſaying, turn in, and the Lord calleth by that of himſelf in you, and reproveth you by his pure witneſs, and ſmiteth you in your Conſciences, I ſay, all turn to that which ſmiteth, checketh and reproveth, that the Lord God may pour forth his Spirit upon you, and cauſe you to know the mind of the Lord, and to feel the word of the Lord, which is nigh you, in your hearts, and is quick, and powerful, ſharper then a two edged ſword, and ſearcheth your hearts, and ſheweth you your hearts, and ſheweth you all your hypocriſie, and how you are hypt from the pure Spirit of the Lord God, and have loſt the Image of the heavenly, and bears the image of the earthly, ſenſual and diveliſh, and in that wiſdom you are with all the world which is enmity with God, and brings not any to the knowledge of God, no more then it brought the Jews to the knowledge of Chriſt, when he came; and this is your woful and ſad Eſtate, and herein are you crying as they were of old, that ye are the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107205:5"/>Church of the Lord, and keep the Ordinances of the Lord, and are crying out againſt them who witneſs Chriſt the ſubſtance, the body, the end of all types, and figures, who is the Everlaſting Day, in which all ſhadows flee away, and he was before all ſhadows was, and they that are out of him, are in the ſhadows, and not they that are in him.</p>
            <p>And your actions plainly declare and make it manifeſt unto all that are not blind, and have not utterly loſt the feeling of the Lord God, that ye are wholly degenerated from the Lord, and inwardly ravened from the Spirit of the Lord God, which gave forth the Scriptures; For both of them bear Teſtimony againſt you, that ye have loſt the ſpiritual weapon, and knows not the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God to defend your ſhadows, types and figures, and all your ordinances, which you in your immaginations have ſet up, and have made to your ſelves many likeneſſes, and fall down to them and worſhip them, and would have all to do the like, as if they were the true God; but God is a Spirit, and all that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth; therefore all come down and feel the ſpirit of the Lord, &amp; the power of the Lord God in you, leading &amp; guiding you out of all the Worlds wayes, and the wickedneſs thereof, and it will lead you by a way which you never went, and in a path which the vulters eye hath not ſeen, nor the fierce lioniſh nature hath not troden therein; But the Children of the Lord, and the redeemed of the Lord walk therein, and a fool cannot erre therein; Therefore all ceaſe from your own wiſdom, which is fooliſhneſs with God, and own Gods wiſdom in you, even the Light which is accounted foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs by you; and all wait low in it, and a ſecret ſtrength and power you ſhall feel Riſe in you as you wait out of all your thoughts, and reaſonings, and imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and then ſhall you feel, and not before, that Gods thoughts are not as your thoughts, nor Gods wayes as your wayes, neither doth the Lord reveal his ſecrets to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who are out of the Babes nature, and childes nature for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107205:5"/>there is not any of them as yet, that is become as a little child, or as a weaned child before the Lord, as <hi>David</hi> was, and how then ſhould you ſee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God; for Chriſt ſaith, a man muſt be regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and become as a child, before that he can ſee the Kingdom of God, and again he ſaith, whoſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives not the Kingdom as a little child, ſhall in no wiſe enter therein; Therefore I ſay again unto you who are in the halings, pullings, and tearings, and uſing Antichriſts weapons, which are not ſpiritual, but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, when any is moved of the Lord, as I have often been, to come to your meetings, and have ſpoken unto you in the Name and dread of the Lord, then have you made it appear that you are yet in the Lions nature, which never trod in the way of the Lord; honeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and ſearch the Scriptures, which you ſay is your rule to walk by, where did you ever find therein that any of the Saints, or people of the Lord, did ever pull and hale any out of their meetings, or elect of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, or make it the work of their Deacons, which ſhould be full of the Holy ghoſt, to pull, or hale any violently out of their meetings? as <hi>Thomas Lamb,</hi> and <hi>William Allin</hi> did, who ſay the Holy Ghoſt hath made them overſeers of the Church of Chriſt, with many more ſuch like actions which ye be found in, beſides many damnable doctrines, which would be too much here to repeat, ſome of which I ſhall ſet down in the following diſcourſe. And this is the judgement of the Lord, and the wrath of the Lord upon you all for your wickedneſs, in that you are ſtill calling your ſelves Chriſtians, and the Church of the Lord, and will not ſee how unlike Chriſt and his Church you are in all theſe actions.</p>
            <p>And many of you who are called Baptiſts have had much tenderneſſe in you formerly, and then was the Lord nearer you, and ye nearer to him then now you are, and then could you begin to ſay, that all the World lay in vanity, by reaſon of which there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107205:6"/>but vexation of ſpirit, and then did many of you, begin to deny reſpect of Perſons, which you ſaw to be ſin; But are now contending for, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of that which you once ſaw vanity in, and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain building that which you once deſtroyed, and ſo are become tranſgreſſors of the Law; But it is happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you according to the true proverb, the dog is returned to his vomit, and the ſow that was waſhed, to the wallowing in the mire. And many of you in thoſe dayes began to deny the worlds faſhions, in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting off your gold, and ſilver, and coſtly attire which you ſaw to be needleſſe, and contrary to the Scripture, and practiſes of the Saints, and not the adorning which the daughters of <hi>Sarah</hi> and the holy women of old were adorned with, and many of you have caſt off your points, fancies, and needleſſe toyes, which then you did wear, but now there is many of you, have got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain your ſilk garters, and fancies, and wear your ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and gold laces, and plead for them, (and ſay they are needful things) and that by your own rule, the Scriptures, with which rule you could formerly plead againſt them; ſo that if one come to your meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, one can behold no difference between you, and the world, which you ſay you are ſeparated from, and who in all the Steeple-houſes can be more full of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity then ſome of your. Teachers and Paſtors are in wearing your cuffs, and ſilver hat-bands, and your hats licked like a ſpotted Leopard; therefore all your ſeparation from the world is but in words, for you are not yet redeemed out of the Worlds wayes, faſhions, friendſhips, and cuſtoms, which are all enmity with God, and muſt paſſe away; but he that doth the will of God, abideth for ever, and can never be moved. And when I conſider theſe things, and whether, and from whence ye are fallen, and how ye have hardened your hearts againſt the Lord, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did, in whoſe preſence, and before whom I was altogether unwilling to write unto you, ſo that I may truly ſay, that I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107205:6"/>do it rather by conſtraint, then willingly; But the ſpirit of the Lord conſtraineth me, which is contrary to mans will in all things, and in obedience to him, whoſe wayes and wiſdom is not as mans, do I write, whether you hear or forbear to hear. And concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the order of your Church, which you ſay is the Church of Chriſt, and you ſay your ſelves are in the Goſpel order and Members thereof, anſwer theſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, where do ye find, or read in the Scriptures, that the Miniſters of Chriſt did ſet up an hour-glaſſe to preach by as ye do; and when that is out, to ſay the time is ſpent? whether your time be in the Fathers hand, or in the hour-glaſſe? or whether the Spirit of the Lord is or ever was limited to an hour-glaſſe? or whether the Saints did not all ſpeak one by one, as the ſpirit gave them utterance?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whether the Saints or Miniſters of Chriſt did invent what to ſay before-hand, and writ it down, as ſome of ye do, and then read it to your Church, or whether they did not ſpeak as the unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Spirit gave them utterance?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Where did the Church of Chriſt ever appoint a certain number of their members to ſpeak at ſet times, and call it diſorder for any to ſpeak beſides them whom they did appoint? and whether they might not all ſpeak one by one, that all may be edified, and all might be comforted? whether this was not the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and not counted confuſion in any of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Saints?</p>
            <p>But Alas, alas! ſo are you fallen, and ſo far dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the Lord, and apoſtatized from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles life, doctrine, and practiſe, and ſo ignorant are you of the letter of the Scriptures, which ye ſay is your rule, and ſo far hath the God of the World blinded your eyes, that now you are ſeting up things that are ſeen which are temporal, created viſible things, and muſt periſh in the uſing thereof; in ſtead of the inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107205:7"/>eternal and unchangeable God, you are ſetting up carnal water in ſtead of the Name of the Lord, which is the nature of God, and is inviſible, and is unchangeable, and one with himſelf, and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as he is unchangeable, and ſo far are ye gone from the Name of the Lord, which is a ſtrong tower, which is the Rock of Ages, and the foundation of many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations; into which name, Chriſt gave his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles commiſſion to teach and Baptize, as ye may read, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. and the three laſt verſes, and Jeſus came and ſpake unto them, ſaying, <hi>All power is given unto me in Heaven and Earth; Go ye therefore and teach all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, baptiſing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, teaching them to obſerve, and to do all things whatſoever I command you, and Lo I am with you alwayes unto the end of the Word</hi> (where there need not that any man teach them) and this you are cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to be water, who have loſt the Name and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Lord which ſhould lead you and guide you into the Scriptures of Truth, and inſtead of this name, which is but one, and this body which is but one, into which bodie the Saints was Baptiſed into the body, by one ſpirit,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.5.</note> whether they were <hi>Jewes</hi> or <hi>Greek,</hi> bound or free, and was made to drink into one ſpirit, and in ſtead of this name ye have got the beaſts names, and the beaſts doctrines, which are Doctrines of Devils and names of blaſphemy, and this in particular I charge upon ye all in preſence of the Lord, and by the power of the Lord God,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.3.</note> who are crying up water, and preaching up water in ſtead of the Name of the Lord God to be a Doctrine of Devils; for Chriſt ſent not his Diſciples to baptize with water, but to preach, and to baptize in the Name, which Name of the Lord conſiſts not in words and ſillables,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 17.1</note> but in purity, Righteouſneſſe, and holineſſe, and is the Divine nature, and the Name of the Lord, as you may read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.5. <hi>And the Lord deſcended in the cloud, and ſtood with him there, and proclaimed the Name of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107205:7"/>the Lord,</hi> and the Nature of the Lord, and the Lord paſſed by him, and proclaimed the Lord, the Lord God, merciful, and gracions, long ſuffering, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant in goodneſs and truth, keeping mercy for thouſands, forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin; and this is the Name of the Lord, and the Nature of the Lord, and beſides this, there is not another name whereby man can be ſaved, but the Name of Jeſus.<note place="margin">Acts 4.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, alas! how doth this ſtagger ye? and how are you in your inventions ſeeking to find it out, &amp; in your own wiſdom are Judging and Condemning them as that Generation did in all Ages, Condemning the Children of the Lord, who had made the Name of the Lord their Tower, and were led by the Spirit of the Lord as Deceivers, Blaſphemers, and Seducers; and ſo he who is the Lord our Righteouſneſs, and the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many Generations, both he &amp; his Name which ye are gone from, is become the ſtone of ſtumbling, and the Rock of offence, and ſet at naught by you builders of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and ſo all in the fear of the Lord God (who are crying up water, and ſetting upwater in ſtead of the Name of the Lord God) honeſtly ſink down to the light of Chriſt, who is the true light, and lighteth every man that comes into the world; and ye ſhall ſee ye have not as yet ſo much as known the Name of the Lord, nor heard thereof, but by the hearing with the carnal ear, as they who were Baptized with water, had not ſo much as heard whether there were a Holy Ghoſt, as ye may read, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. to the 7. verſe, When they heard this, they were Baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus; but how ſhould it be otherwiſe with you, who are yet in the worlds faſhions, &amp; cuſtoms, and who is ſo blind as he that is perfect in ye in whom the god of this world hath blinded the eye, which ſhould be your leader, teacher and inſtructor, and leadeth in the way of Righteouſneſs, and cauſeth all that follow him to inherit ſubſtance; he it is who is the Light of the world, and is not of the world, but leadeth all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107205:8"/>that follow him out of the world, its friendſhips, faſhions and cuſtoms which ye are in, and yet ſay, you are ſeparated from them, and ſay, you are Jewes, and are not, but are of the ſynagogue of Sathan, and are found Blaſphemers therein; and thus ye have ſet up the Idol in your hearts, and put the ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block of Iniquity before my face, ſaith the Lord God, and turned away the face of mine Annointed, and have caſt the Law of the Lord behinde your backs, and have rejected the Light of the Lord in you, which is the Word of the Lord, and know not God, Chriſt, nor his Spirit, but in your thoughts, where God is not to be found, and therein have ye imagined a God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Clouds, and afar off, but know not the Chriſt who is the expreſs Image of the Fathers perſon, to reveal the Father in you; even he who is born of the Spirit, and is Spirit, and the onely begotten of the Spirit, the Glory of him, I ſay, you are change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your vain Imaginations into the glory of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. to the end, read your ſtate there. And you are ſpeaking of a Chriſt, ſome of you of five foot long, and asking how he can dwell in a man, &amp; calling it blaſphemy to ſay, that Chriſt which ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of five foot long, can be in a man; thus you are in your imaginations, and therein have ſet up a carnal Chriſt in your carnal minds, but to this day; are altogether ignorant, as <hi>Philip</hi> was, <hi>John</hi> 3.8. Read and underſtand,<note place="margin">John 14.8.</note> if you have an ear to hear what the Spirit ſaith, and ſee how you are gazing, and are at a loſs, as the men of <hi>Galilee</hi> were, while the vail is over your hearts, and the Cloud hath taken him out of your ſight; and the are you ſcattered upon all the dark mountains of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and have wandred from the Lord, the living Fountain, and are like <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove, toſſed upon the waters, and knowes not a reſting place for the ſole of your foot. Therefore all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, Return to the light of the Lord in your Conſciences, that you may feel a Rock to ſtay and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107205:8"/>lean upon, and he is not far from any of you, there is none of you need to ſay, who ſhall deſcend or aſcend to fetch him up from beneath, or bring him down from above, but what ſaith it, the word is nigh thee, in thy heart, that thou mayeſt obey it, and do it; and this is your fallen eſtate, ſaith the Lord, God, which know not Chriſt in you the hope of glory. Even the ſame that was before the world was, one with the Father, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Heaven &amp; earth, and was never ſeen with any car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal eye, nor his voice heard by any carnal ear, but in the pure eternal, unchangeable light is he revealed and ſeen more and more, as it is written, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. For with thee is the Fountain of life, in thy light ſhall we ſee light, and ſo the way of the Juſt (and the ſeed of the Juſt, which is as a grain of Muſtard ſeed) is as a ſhining light that ſhineth more and more, until the perfect day, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.3. Then ſhall we know the Lord, whoſe goings forth is prepered as the morning; therefore none de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the day of ſmall things, nor none reject the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, but come tot his help againſt the Mighty, nor reject the ſeed of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe it is in bondage, and lieth in thick darkneſs, and ſhineth in thick dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but all ſink down that ye may feel the Arm of the Lord, and witneſs <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to do valiantly, and to ſmite down all, and break, and hammer down all which is exalted, and hath been exalted above him, and lick up Nations, and lick up people, as the Oxe licketh up graſs, and ſcatter Nation, and ſcatter peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and threſh the Mount of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſcatter the duſt thereof, and burn up the thorns, and bryars thereof, as the wind doth ſcatter the chaff, and the fire devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the dry ſtubble, (but read within) thus ſhall it be when the Lord ariſeth in you to ſhake terribly the earth, &amp; overturn the mountains by the roots, and dry up the Sea by his Power, and ſmite through the proud by his Power, <hi>Jude</hi> 26.11, 12. And ſo who waits love in patience upon the Lord God, ſhall come to know what it is to be Baptized into the Name of the Lord God,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107205:9"/>when they feel the Name of the Lord, and ſee the Name of the Lord to be exalted in them above every name, and to know the Mountain of the Lords Houſe eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a-top of every mountain; Then ſhall come to paſs that ſaying, &amp; not till then, which is written, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.14. Then ſhalt thou delight thy ſelf in the Lord, and I will cauſe thee to ride upon the high places of the earth, and feed thee with the heritage of <hi>Jacob</hi> thy Father, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it; then ſhall ye know the builder of the waſte places, and the raiſer up of the foundation of many Generations, the repairer of the breach, the reſtorer of the pathes to dwell in, then ſhall the beaſt and his many names, the King and his many Nobles be all brought under, and bound with fetters of iron, as ye may read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.9. Let the Saints be joyful in Glory, let them ſing aloud upon their beds, let the High praiſes of the Lord be in their mouths, and a two edged ſword in their hands, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute vengeance upon the Heathen, and puniſhments upon the people, to bind their Kings with chaines, and their Nobles with fetters of Iron, to execute upon them the Judgements written, this honour have all the Saints, Praiſe ye the Lord, Mark, read and underſtand, not ſhall have, as you turn it hereafter, but this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour have all the Saints who were in all ages bound, &amp; fettered themſelves by the wicked Rulers of the earth. But before you can ſee or believe theſe things, that eye which ye now ſee with, muſt be blinded, and the eye which the god of the world hath blinded, muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, &amp; then he that ſpeaks not of himſelf, but of the Father, nor receives honour of man, but of the Father; then, and not till then will his Words be plain unto you, and not parables. But all ye that are ſpeaking of yourſelves, know neither the Son nor the Father, ye that can pray when you will, and preach when you will, and when you will can be ſilent, and all this is but in your own will, and in your own time, but ye have neither heard the voice of the Father at any time,<note place="margin">Jo. 5.37.</note> nor
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107205:9"/>ſeen his ſhape, but are inwardly ravened from the Spirit of the Father, in whoſe hands your time ſhould be rather then in an hour-glaſs, which ye think the Spirit of the Lord will be limitted unto; for when that is run, ye ſay, the time is expired; and this is contrary to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles practice, which ſpake as the Spirit gave them utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which ye may read, was until midnight, <hi>Acts</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.7. And thus the Scripture, which you ſay, is your Rule to walk by, beareth witneſs againſt you, that ye walk contrary to it; And yet ſo blind are ye, that are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning us as Apoſtates which are led by the Spirit of the Lord, and not contrary to the Scriptures, and will not ſee that ye your ſelves are led neither by Letter nor Spirit; But in your thoughts and imaginations ye are, and ye ſee with the beaſts eyes which are many, and ſo are in the many minds, and many heads, and divided into the many bodies, being led by the many eyes of the beaſt, and with his many horns are thruſting and kicking one againſt another, but know not the body, nor diſcern not the body of Chriſt which is but one, neither know the one eye which is the Spirit of truth to be your guider, &amp; leader into all truth; But one is crying, I am of this mind, and another I am of this, and ye being many are of many minds, and ſee with the beaſts eyes which are many, and all about the meaning of ſome one particular Scripture; but are all gone from the Spirit of the Lord which gave forth the Scriptures, and did ſpeak as it meant, which Spirit is but one in all his Children, and all that are led by it are led into oneneſs, and they are of one heart, and one Soul as they that were guided by this one ſpirit in all ages was, what ever you may imagine who are far from knowing ſuch a ſtate; but one of you is crying, I am for general Redemption, and another, I am for particular Election; one is for eating of blood, and another is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, ſome for waſhing of feet, and others own it not, one for laying on of hands, and another againſt it, and ſome that have preached it up as an Ordinance of Chriſt, as <hi>William Allen,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Lamb,</hi> and without it ſaid,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107205:10"/>they could not admit any into the body of Chriſt, and now themſelves are gone from that alſo, and look upon it as an indifferent thing, and ſome of them are ſo blind that they ſay they cannot call any Brother until they have been Baptized in the water, though it be but an hour before they are Baptized, and yet a moneth before that, when they have Examined them about their Faith, and have judged them believers; and I ſay, that all are the Sons of God by Faith, and therefore read, <hi>Gal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.26. And conſider what an Idol you have made of carnal wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that cannot have fellowſhip with the Sons, of God, until they fall down to worſhip the Idol which ye in your Imaginations have ſet up, for which ye have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Spirit nor the Letter of the Scriptures to own you in. Some of you ſay that Chriſt ſhall come and reign among you a thouſand years hereafter, but that ye ſay, ye know not when it ſhall be; and many of you are for a Supper before that which ye call the Lords Supper, and many of you deny both theſe; thus are yow <hi>Babels</hi> builders, ſcattered and confounded among your ſelves in your Imaginations, where you are building up, and flinging down that which ye have built, and ſo makes your ſelves tranſgreſſors; and upon you all this is the plague of the Lord God, for many of you have been convinced in your Conſciences when I was amongſt you, that all things were out of Order, and that ye were not as ye ſhould be, but now are again pleading and contending for them, and are licking up that which ye ſometime vomited out, and thus are you reſtleſs and out of peace, as the wicked are, who are like the troubled Sea; and ye are gone from the Rock of ages,<note place="margin">Iſa 58.12</note> and know not the Foundation of many generations, and have laid another foundation then Chriſt Jeſus the Corner-ſtone, which is ſmiting at the feet of your Image which ye in your I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations have ſet up, and the Lord God of life and power will over-turn, over-turn, over-turn, until he Reign, whoſe Right it is to Reign, and the Lord hath dryed up the Sea, &amp; hath diſcovered to his Children your
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107205:10"/>Foundation, you who know not what it is, nor how any can be Baptized into the Name of the Lord, which is the Nature of the Lord, which Name none knowes, ſaving he that hath it, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. He that hath an ear let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches, to him that overcome will I give to eat of the hidden Manna, and I will give him a white ſtone, and in this ſtone a new Name written, which no man knowes ſaving he that receiveth it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12. And I will write upon him the Name of my God, and the Name of the City of my God, which is new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which cometh down out of Heaven from my God, and I will write upon him my new Name, he that hath an ear let him hear what the Spirit ſaith. But you who are in the Myſtery of iniquity, are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended with the Myſtery of God, and your bottom ſeen, and your ſandy foundation diſcovered, and the Beaſt Rules and Reigns amongſt you, as I have ſaid before, and ye are kicking and thruſting down one another, who are gone from the Name of the Lord, and power of the Lord, and ye are in the many heads, and many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1. And I ſaw a beaſt riſe up out of the Sea; and here is all your foundation, even in the waters, and ye have all drunk of the Cup which is in the right hand of the Whore, with whom the Kings of the earth have committed fornication, which ſitteth upon many waters, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2, 4. And upon her fore-head was a name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> the great Mother of Harlots, and the great abomination of the Earth, and I ſaw the woman of the Martyrs of Jeſus, and when I ſaw her, I wondered with great admiration. And here is the mind that hath wiſdom, for the woman which thou ſaweſt is that great City which reigneth over the Kings of the Earth, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. And he ſaid unto me, the waters which thou ſaweſt where the Whore ſitteth, are Peoples and Multitudes, Nations and Tongues, and this is the ſtate of all Nations, and Multitudes, an Peoples whatſoever of all Sects and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, Bodies and Heads, who we gone from the one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107205:11"/>Body, and one Head, but know not the Name of the Lord, and are not Baptized into the Name of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. For by one Spirit were they all Baptized into one Body; and this is your ſtate in particular who are called <hi>Baptists,</hi> who are toſſed up and down in your Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and are as unſtable as waters,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.4.</note> and wavering as the waves of the Sea, and are contending for ſhadowes and variable and changing things, and are gone from the Rock of ages and from the ſure Foundation, and Tried-ſtone which ſtandeth above the waters, and in whom there is no ſhadow nor variableneſs, neither ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of turning. Therefore to you all this is the Word of the Lord God, come down to the Rock, &amp; feel the Rock out of all your Thoughts, Reaſonings and Imaginations, that you may eat the Bread of Life, and be ſatisfied; not as the fathers did eat Manna in the Wilderneſs, and are dead; neither as you are eating your carnal bread; or drinking your carnal wine, which bread muſt periſh, and go into the drought, and that which eateth it muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the duſt as it was; but that a man eat hereof, and live for ever. <hi>John</hi> 6.46. to the 61. Therefore all own that which will purifie you which is the Spirit of the Lord God; a meaſure of which Spirit is given to every one of you to profit withal, and ſo that will create in you a clean heart, and anew heart, as you obey it; and then ſhall you come to witneſs the new wine in the new bottle, and ſo both are preſerved, and neither ſpilt; and ſaith Chriſt, I will not henceforth drink any more the fruit of the vine until I drink it new with you in my Fathers Kingdom; for the Spirit was not yet given, nor the day was not yet come, nor the ſhadows fled away. But you are eating and diſcern not the Lords Body, and ye are drinking Condemnation to your ſelves, and wo be to all that eat, and Chriſt is not with them in their eating, for they know not the Word to ſanctifie that which they eat; but you are eating in the contention, in the ſtriving about words, wherein there is no profit, and one is covetous, and another is proud; and this is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107205:11"/>not to eat with ſingleneſs of heart, as they did (whom ye ſay) ye imitate, who was then of one heart, and one Soul, as the children of the Lord who are led by the light of the Lord are now, whatever you may falſly ſlander them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and ſo your table is become a ſnare unto you, in whom the God of the World ruleth, and hath blinded the eye which ſhould diſcern the Lords body, and your table is a table of Devils, and ye cannot pertake of the Table of the Lord, and the table of the Devils. But the Lord hath bleſſed us, and we are bleſſed, and curſed is every one that curſeth us, and we ſit round about our Fathers Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and we eat bread in our Fathers houſe, and ſit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our own vine, and we drink of the new wine with him in our Fathers Kingdom; and bleſſed are all them that eat bread in the Kingdom of God, for they eat their bread with ſingleneſs of heart, out of all ſtrife and contention, out of all tranſgreſſion and ſin, and we witneſſe him who doth finiſh tranſgreſſion, and puts an end to ſin, and brings us into his everlaſting righteouſneſs, and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe we know (which is not as filthy raggs) even the white linen which is the Saints righteouſneſſe, and it is become unto us as a garment, and to us it is a Helmet of Salvation, and we are in him, and not in our own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; and he that is in him, and followes him, is led in the way of righteouſneſſe, and ſinneth not, <hi>John</hi> 5.1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6. whoſoever abideth in him ſinneth not, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſinneth hath not ſeen him, nor known him, and all ye that are commiting ſin, and preaching for ſin, and diſputing for ſin, and ſay none can be perfect and free from ſin while they live, you are all of your father the Devil, for the Devil ſineth from the beginning, and the work of the Devil hath been wrought in you, and the luſts of the fleſh, and the pride of life is brought forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, and for this purpoſe is the Son of God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, that he may deſtroy the works of the Devil; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is born of God doth not commit ſin, for his ſeed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin becauſe he is born of God; for thus ſaith the Lord, I planted thee a Noble
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107205:12"/>vine, and I made thee an upright plant; how art thou become the degenerate plant of a ſtrange vine unto me ſaith the Lord? And ſo you are degenerated from the Lord, and eſtranged from the life which is the Light of man, and ye are without God in the World, and the world lieth in darkneſſe, and the light ſhineth in darkneſſe, <hi>Jc.</hi> 1. and the darkneſſe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendes it not, and in this ſtate you are, who are pleading for ſin, and cannot ceaſe from ſin, as ye may read, <hi>Ro.</hi> 3.12. they are all gone out of the way, they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become abominable, there is none that doth good, no not one, their throat is an open Sepulchre, with their tongues they have uſed deceit, the poiſon of Aſps is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their lips, but the way of peace they have not known; and this is the reaſon why you cannot ceaſe from ſin, 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 2.14, 15. becauſe ye have forſaken the right way, as thoſe curſed children which he ſpeaks of had, and had erred in their hearts from the light which is the way, the power of God, and wiſdom of God; and ſo blind are you notwithſtanding all this, that ye preach, and pray ſometimes againſt all ſin, and ſay you know it is your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to abſtain from all appearance of evil, and to preſs and to ſtrive after perfection, and yet connot ſee that your ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is ſin, and your preaching againſt, and ſtriving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, is ſin; for all that is not of faith is ſin; for this is contrary to your belief, that men can be perfect and free from ſin, and your ſelves being gone out of the waie, and ſtriving againſt ſin, while out of the waie, to you the commands of God muſt needs appear to be hard and grevious, you being gone from the light, the power which makes his waies, waies of pleaſantneſſe, and all his paths and commands eaſie, and is not this the command of God? Be ye holy, for I the Lord am holy, and be you perfect, as your Heavenly Father is perfect, and that you ſhould abſtain not onely from the evil, but from all appearance of evil, and <hi>Paul</hi> who was an Elder and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt, he praied in the Name of the Lord, and his praier was not in vain as yours are, who pray for that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107205:12"/>which ye believe can never be, who praied that the Saints might be kept blameleſſe and ſpotleſſe, both in ſoul, bodie, and ſpirit, until the coming of the Lord; and to preſent the Churches as a chaſte virgin, and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſpouſe to the Lord without ſpot or wrinkle, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſuch thing; and was it not <hi>Pauls</hi> work to preſent everie man perfect in Chriſt? and did he work and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vain, as ye do, or ſtrive in vain, or preach in vain, who ſaid he preached wiſdom in a miſterie to them that were perfect? and doth not <hi>John</hi> ſay, 1 <hi>John,</hi> 2.14. when he ſpake to the young men and fathers, doth not he tell them, that greater was he that was in them, then he that was in the world, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 4.4. And they were ſuch as had the word abiding in them, and they kept themſelves that the wicked one touched them not, and they were led by the ſpirit it of the Lord, and walked in the light of the Lord, and brought their words, and all their actions to the tryer and touch-ſtone, which is the Law, and the Teſtamony, which law is light ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Proverbs.</hi> 6. and which. Teſtimony is the ſpirit of propheſie ſaith <hi>John. Rev.</hi> 19.10. and this is bound up, and ſealed with his Diſciples, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.19 20. and this is the word of reconciliation, and reconciles to the Lord all that follow it, and this is the light of the World, and all that follow it are led out of darkneſſe and all ſin, and this is hated by you whatever you ſay who live in ſin; for all that do evil, hate Chriſt, all who are full of vain words, and uſe vain words, and all which are in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions of the World, and love and friendſhips of the World, even this is the condemnation of them all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they hate it and love it not; and no man is juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſight of God, nor hath peace with God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he reconciled unto God, who is not led and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by that which reconciles unto the Father; therefore all you that ſpeak of being juſtified by Chriſt, and ſay you do believe in Chriſt, and yet your ſelves are found ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, deceive not your ſelves my friends, for it is hard for you to believe againſt Gods witneſſe, and to ſpeak
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107205:13"/>peace to your ſelves, while Gods witneſſe in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciences ſpeaks war, and condemnation; for man muſt be regenerated and born again of the immortal word, which word is like a fire, and like a hammer, and as you wait, lo ye ſhall feel it ſo, and it will break down, and ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer down that which ſeparates you from the Lord, it will finiſh tranſgreſſion and condemn ſin in you, it will rent the vail, and deſtroy the covering which is over the heart; and ſo will purifie you, and open the pure eye which can ſee the Lord, and open the deaf ear which can hear what the ſpirit ſaith, &amp; the grave ſhall be opened, and the priſoner of hope ſhall come out of the pit where there is no water, and he that hath been your condemnation ſhall now become your Saviour, and he that hath been ſlain ſince the foundation of the World, ſhall live in you, and the great miſtery of Godlineſſe ſhall be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to you, which is Chriſt in you the hope of glory, and Satan which hath been exalted in you, even in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, above all that is called God, and the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which makes deſolate, and the great miſterie of iniquity ſhall then be ſeen by the great miſtery of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and then ſhall come to paſſe, and ye ſhall come to witneſſe it true without a meaning, that which is written by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.1. the Wilderneſſe and the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary place ſhall be glad, and the deſert ſhall rejoyce and bloſſom as the roſe; then ſhall the eyes of the blind be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and the ears of the deaf ſhall be unſtopped, then ſhall the lame man leap as an hart, and the tongue of the dumb ſing, for in the Wilderneſſe ſhall waters break out, and ſtreams in the deſert, and the ranſomed of the Lord ſhall return and come to <hi>Zion</hi> with ſongs and everlaſting joy upon their heads, they ſhall obtain joy and gladneſs, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away, and then ſhall the parable be opened, and plainneſſe to you when you have found the key of <hi>David,</hi> unto whom the parable is not, I ſay when you have found the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets writ of, then ſhall you leave your figures, your ſhadowes, and types, when you wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107205:13"/>the Prophet raiſed up in you, who is the life and ſubſtance, and the everlaſting day, and the Lord of the Sabbaoth, then ſhall you leave your images, and caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your Idols, and leave off your idolatry, and follow the Lamb where-ever he goeth, and then ſhall you know that Scripture, which ye have been ſo much in your ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, about to know the meaning of, <hi>Zach.</hi> 10 11, 12. and then ſhall you ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſearched with candles, and the inhabitants of <hi>Judah</hi> with torches, and the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things of <hi>Eſan</hi> brought to light, and the ſeed of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> which hath bowed to <hi>Eſaus</hi> ſeed, ſhall bow no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger but until he be paſt, and then ſhall <hi>Babylon</hi> the great, the tumultuous city, and golden city, and city of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion be broken down, and that in which the blood of the innocent hath been found, and the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus, and the blood of the ſouls of them that lies ſlain under the Altar, crying, how long thou holy and juſt God, ſhall all be required at her hands, and come into remembrance with the Lord God, and he that hath ſlain with the ſword ſhall be killed with the ſword, and he that hath led into captivity; and here is the mind that hath wiſdom, and here is the patience of the Saints, and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> the great is fallen, is fallen, and then ſhall ye know <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the new city, even new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> become a peaceable habitation, and then ſhall ye be gathered into general aſſembly, and ſhall come to the ſpirit of juſt men made perfect, and unto <hi>Mount Zion,</hi> and unto the city of the living God, the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable company of Angels, and general aſſembly and Church of the firſt-born, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12 22 24 and unto God the judge of all, and to Jeſus the Reconciler, and Mediator of the new Covenant, and to the blood of ſprinkling, which ſpeaketh better things then that of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſ,</hi> and then ſhall your water, even your foundation be ſhaken, and nothing ſhall ſtand with you, but the Rock of Ages which cannot be moved, verſ. 27 and in the preſence and power of the Lord God, I warn you all, put not this day a far off, which is the joyful day and year
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107205:14"/>of Jubile to his people, and the day of <hi>Zions</hi> deliverance to his choſen, which have overcome by the blood of the Lamb, and by the word of his Teſtimony and patience which they do keep, and thereby have made an enterance into the Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.9.</note> and are become companions in tribulation, and in the Kingdom and patience of Jeſus, and are come from far, and knows our manſions in our Fathers houſe, and know the reſt which remains for the people of God, and are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into one ſheep-fold, and witneſſe the Lord our ſhepherd, and we ſee his ſhape, and hear his voice, and follow him who is inviſible, eternal, and unchangeable, and abides a Prieſt for ever, and a ſhelter and a hiding place for ever, and with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> do we ſit in our Fathers Kingdom, and our place of defence is the munition of Rocks, and our bread is ſure, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is given, and the Lord is become our King, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, and we rain with him upon earth, and he hath made us Kings, and Prieſts to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od the Father, and we ſit with him in Heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus, even him who rules the heathen with a rod of iron, and it is he who doth all our workes in us, and for us, and ſlayes our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and breaks our enemies like a potters veſſel, and the ſharp two edged ſword, and the new threſhing inſtrument which hath teeth, we know wherewith he hath threſhed our mountains, and laid them waſte with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Inhabitants, and is now threſhing your mountains, and is breaking down, and ſcattering you, and he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>girding your loines, which are girding your ſelves, and have made to your ſelves likeneſſes, but have loſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth, and ye have joyned your ſelves to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and have eat the ſacrifice of the dead, and have learned their works, and ye are like <hi>Ephraim</hi> feeding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wind, and that which withers and dies of it ſelf, and in this woful, and lamentable ſtate are ye all, who are not lead, guided and acted by the light; and ſo your prayers are as if ye ſlew a man, and all your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices is as the bleſſing of an Idol or offering of Swines
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107205:14"/>fleſh; for you have choſen your own wayes, and are gone from the way of the Lord, and light of the Lord, and ye have ſet up the idol in your hearts, and ye live in that, and delight in that, and are led by that which my ſoul abhors ſaith the Lord, and ye have ſet up the letter for your rule in ſtead of the new creature, and life, and ye have ſet up the Babel, which is ink and paper to be your judge, and tryer of the anointing, and with that ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Innocent, and judge him unto whom all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is committed, as the blind Jewes, who were pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a profeſſion as you are, but were inwardly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened, and gone from the anointing in them, which was, and for ever ſhall be the Saints tryer, and judge of the ſpirits which lead out into the World, and he is the ſame to his children as ever he was, and his ſons pray, and preach, and are led by his ſpirit as ever they were, though ye cannot believe theſe which are apoſtatized from the Apoſtles doctrine, and have ſet up carnal, created, viſible things, and have ſet up water in ſtead of the Name of the Lord, and the letter in ſtead of the life of the Lord, and ye have put the letter, and your meaning thereof, and your private interpretations which ye have added to be the rule, the tryer, and the leader of the Saints, and the law, and the Teſtimony, and the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Spirits, and all theſe have ye ſet up above Chriſt, who is the ſpiritual man, who judgeth all things, and ought to be your judge in all things, and to whom all power and judgement is given, and committed in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, and he himſelf is judged of no man; and ſo the beam is in your eye, and the mote in your eye, end ye being hipt from the pure of God, and with that which hath been exalted above all that is called God, are ye judging and condemning the Son of God, unto whom all judgement is committed; but this is your day, and the power of darkneſſe, and the regin of the Lord, and the day of the Lord, which ye ſo much talk of ſhall come hereafter, you ſhall then hide your ſelves in the dens of the earth, and cave of the earth, and the mountains ſhall you deſire to fall upon you, and the hills, to cover
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107205:15"/>you from the preſence of the Lamb that ſitteth upon the throne, and this day to you ſhall be as you may read, <hi>Amos,</hi> 5. a wofull day, and a day of darkneſſe and not light, as if a man did flee from a Lion, and a Bear met him, or went into the houſe, and leaned his hand on the wall, and a Serpent bit him, verſ 8 2, but as I ſaid before to you, even judgement (which ye have turned back, let that run down as waters, and righteouſneſſe, as a mighty ſtream; But you have borne the tabernacle of <hi>Molock,</hi> and <hi>Chion,</hi> your images, the ſtar of your God which you make to your ſelves, and ſo Chriſts perſonal reign which ye are ſpeaking of and expecting, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing after without, as the men of <hi>Galilee</hi> were, ſhall be upon you, and unto you the day of the Lords controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, the day of the Lords vengeance, and a time of the Lords controverſie unto you, and upon you who are not led by the light of the Lord, &amp; the ſpirit of the Lord; and that none may ſay, that I accuſe you falſly, and ſo condemn you, you being innocent, read a book of <hi>Henry Haggers,</hi> and a book of <hi>John Goſnels,</hi> entituled a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Baptiſme of the water, and of the ſpirit, page the 38. Where in plain words, he ſetteth up the water above the Name of the Lord, and there he confeſſeth as <hi>Epheſians,</hi> 4.5. That there is but one Baptiſm, to ſpeak properly, which is Baptiſm of water, and the other two are but figurative, and metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical; and thus you may ſee that ye blinds Baptiſts are calling water-Baptiſm, which <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. calleth but a figure, and the one Baptiſm, and the only one that Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles to Baptize into, which is into the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, which ye may read, <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19, 20. This he calleth figurative, and metaphorical, and ſo he ſetteth up the figure in ſtead of the body and life of all figures and ſhadowes; and <hi>John</hi> ſaith who was in the figure, I indeed Baptize with water, I muſt decreaſe; but he that cometh after me is preferred before me, he muſt increaſe, who ſhall Baptize with the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107205:15"/>and with fire, and <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. That by one Spirit, whether Jew or Gentile, Bond or Free, they were all Bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed into one Body, and was all made to drink into one Spirit; and this <hi>John Goſnel</hi> calls the figure, even the Name of the Lord, and water which was a figure thereof, he ſetteth up above; and <hi>Henry Hagger</hi> in his Book, he ſaith, the Scripture is the ingrafted Word, and able to make a man Wiſe to Salvation, and throughly to furn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh a man to every good work; and in a Diſpute in <hi>Stafford</hi>-Shire, he ſaid it were ſufficient that he were ſaved by the water; and he told me, that the Letter was the Word of God, and the Judger and Tryer of ſpirits; and this in the preſence and fear of the Lord God, I charge upon you al, who are of this perſwaſion to be guilty of Blaſphemy, &amp; doctrine of Devils, and to deny the Lord that bought you, and to be in the many bodies, and many heads, and ſeeing with the many eyes of the Beaſt, and to have the many names of Blaſphemy, but know not the one Name nor the one Head, neither the Baptiſm into the one Body and Name, whereby man can be ſaved, read and underſtand <hi>Acts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.12. Neither is there Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any other, for there is no other Name under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven given amongſt men, whereby we muſt be ſaved, but the Name which is ſet at naught by you builders, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſtumbling ſtone, and a Rock of offence; but unto us that believe he is precious and a tryed ſtone, and the power of God to Salvation, and with him and by him, we deny all your ſhadows, and all your figures, and all your waſhings which makes nothing perfect; and thoſe which the Scriptures own, we deny not any one of them, as the brazen Serpent, offerings, and Circumciſion, and Baptiſm, all of which had a beginning, and were impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but till the time of a through Reformation,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.7.</note> and makes nothing perfect, but all were to end and do end in him who is the bringer in of the better hope, and is not made after the Law of a carnal commandment, but after the power of an Endleſs life, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.9. And perfects for ever them that are ſanctified, and makes peace, and keeps in peace all that believe in him, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107205:16"/>takes away ſin as pertaining to the Conſcience; and ſo comes the Myſtery of Faith to be witneſſed to be held in a pure Conſcience, which Faith I charge upon you to bee Reprobates concerning, let your prayers and profeſſions be what they will; as <hi>Jeremy Ives,</hi> and <hi>William Anſworth,</hi> two of your chief Teachers have denied the Faith, which is the Gift of God, and calls it the creatures Act, which is contrary to the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Jude</hi> 3. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the Faith that once was delivered or given to the Saints, and all your faith in general, which gives you not power over all ſin, but in it you can be pleading for, and Diſputing for ſin, and ſay, none can be perfect in this life; We Rank you altogether, and by the power of the Lord we judge you altogether to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates concerning the faith; read <hi>Acts</hi> 15. and <hi>John</hi> 9.1. and 3.2, 3. to the tenth, and your hope is but the hope of the hypocrite which doth not purifie you as Chriſt is pure, but this muſt needs be ſo with you who are in your own works and faith which makes nothing perfect, and ſay faith is not the gift of God, but an act of the creatures, which muſt needs be imperfect; for <hi>James</hi> ſaith, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good and perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of Lights, <hi>James</hi> 1.7. With whom is no variableneſs, neither ſhadow of turning; but you that are in the ſhadows, and out of the Light, and are in the Errour concerning the Faith, verſe 16. and are reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Faith which is the gift of God, and was once given unto the Saints, <hi>Jud.</hi> 3. And this was held forth at a meeting, by one <hi>William Anſworth, Robert Ward,</hi> and ſeveral others of the Baptiſt teachers, at <hi>Henry Smiths,</hi> at <hi>Wythcock</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter</hi>-Shire, upon the twentyſeventh day of the twelfth moneth, called February, in the year of Account 1658. Before a great number of people, with many other Blaſphemous doctrines; a few of the witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes their names are here written.</p>
            <list>
               <item>FRANCIS CREEK,</item>
               <item>WILLIAM ATTON,</item>
               <item>WILLIAM SLYEE,</item>
               <item>WILLIAM SMITH,</item>
               <item>JOSEPH HOULT,</item>
               <item>MARGERET BEEBY,</item>
               <item>THOMAS HARVEY,</item>
               <item>ISABEL HACKER.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:107205:16"/>
            <p>ANd becauſe you may not ſay that I wrong you, in ſaying that you have ſet up Shadows, Types, and Figures above the Life and Subſtance which is Chriſt, and viſible carnal periſhing things above the Inviſible unchangeable Word of the Lord which endures for ever, I ſhall here ſet down a few of your principal Doctrines, by which ye Judge the principals of Chriſt, and they that are found therein to be Apoſtates, and deceivers, which I ſhall here mention, and anſwer ſomething there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and ſo leave it to Gods witneſs in ye all, to Judge whether you are deceivers and Apoſtates, or we.</p>
            <p>And I am troubled for you all, &amp; my heart is broken for you all, who are hardning your ſelves againſt the Lord, and like the Jewes have painted your ſelves as the Jewes did, who were the greateſt enemies of the Lord, when he came; and I am pained at my very heart for you all, and my life bears the Iniquitie of many, and I am preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a Cart is preſſed that is full of ſheaves, for your mountain is exalted above the Lord, and great is the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Holy ſeed (read and underſtand) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5, 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.4. The ſorrows of death compaſs me, the floods of ungodly men made me afraid, the ſorrows of Hell compaſs me about, the ſnares of death prevented me; <hi>verſe</hi> 11. He made thick darkneſs his ſecret place, and his pavillion round about were dark waters, and thick clouds of the skies, the Lord alſo thundreth in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and the Higheſt gave his voice, hail-ſtones, and coals of fire, ye, he ſent out his Arrows, and ſcattered them; then the Channels of water were ſeen, and the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World were diſcovered, read <hi>Iames</hi> 3.6. If you have an ear to hear what the Spirit, ſaith at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke of the Lord, at the blaſt of the breath of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, he ſent from above and took me, he drew me out of many waters, he delivered me from my ſtrong enemy, and from them which hated me, for they were too ſtrong for me, he brought me forth alſo into a large place he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered me becauſe he dilighted in me, verſe the 18. and 19.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107205:17"/>
            <p> Your firſt principle is this, held forth at that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That faith is an act of the creatures, and not Gods gift: But becauſe I have ſpoken ſomething to this alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: I ſhall add theſe Scriptures for the Reader, and leave it, <hi>Ephiſians</hi> 2 8 and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. And all our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes is as filthy rages, but the Lord worketh all our works in us, and for us; and what is not of faith, is ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That a wicked man, whileſt a wicked m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt, and hath acceſſe unto, and may freely lay hold upon all the merits of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I ſay, you are they which juſtifie your ſelves, being wicked and out of the faith which ſhould purifie your hearts, and ſeek to be juſtified by Chriſt, while your ſelves are found ſinners, and ſo would make Chriſt as you are, Miniſters of ſin, <hi>Galathians,</hi> 2.17. But he that juſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the righteous, as ye do, even they are both an abominate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Lord, <hi>Prov</hi> 17.15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Bible was the life of their ſouls, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> To this I ſay, miſerable are you, and miſerable are all your comforters, who have ſet up another comforter then the conſolation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and the comforts of God, and the conſolations of God are ſmall in you, read <hi>John,</hi> 14 16 17. And ſaith Chriſt, I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever; even the ſpirit of truth, whom the World cannot receive, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him, but you know him, for he dwelleth with you, and ſhall be in you; I will not leave you comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, I will come unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Ainſworth</hi> did affirm, and <hi>John Brown</hi> likewiſe, at his fathers houſe, that <hi>Paul</hi> in baptiſing with water, and not by commiſſion was wicked, and acted wickedly therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, I ſhall prove, what I there then did affirm;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107205:17"/>That <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to Baptize, neither was his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Baptize with water, but into the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; as you may read, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. Though <hi>Iohn Goſnel</hi> be ſo blind, who is one of your chief Teachers, in the firſt page of his book, ſaith it is with water, and ſaith it is not the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of the ſpirit; but if you will believe <hi>John Goſnel</hi> rather then the Scriptures, which you ſay is your rule; Let it be upon your own heads for ever.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall prove they did Baptize with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by permiſſion, and not by commiſſion, if you can either believe <hi>Paul</hi> or the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14. I thank God, I baptized none of you but <hi>Criſpus,</hi> and <hi>Gaius</hi> and I Baptized alſo the houſe of <hi>Stephanus,</hi> and I know not whether I baptized any other; and this he ſaith is the reaſon and ground, verſ. 17. for Chriſt ſent me not to Baptize, but to preach the Goſpel; and I ſay he did this and many other things by permiſſion, as you may read <hi>Acts,</hi> 16.3. where he circumciſed <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> that he might gain and bring ſome to the true circumciſion, and one Baptiſme, <hi>Acts,</hi> 21.24. Where <hi>Paul</hi> ſhaved his head, and all this was by permiſſion, and not by command: And I leave it upon you to prove that he acted wickedly therein; and ſo you may ſee, that thoſe things which you are making your foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and ſetting up above the Name of the Lord, could be done, or left undone by them who were gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſpirit of the Lord; and all was to gain ſome unto the Lord, and bring them into the one Baptiſm, which is by one ſpirit into the Name of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 yet I do not deny water Baptiſm, nor <hi>John</hi> who had a commiſſion to Baptize with water, in their time and in their place, for I do believe and know it was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommand of God, and they that rejected it, rejected the counſel of God, in not being baptized with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>John:</hi> But <hi>John</hi> ſaith of himſelf, I indeed Baptize you with water unto repentance, I muſt decreaſe, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107205:18"/>he muſt encreaſe, who baptizeth with the Holy Ghoſt and fire, and you do not read in all the Scriptures that <hi>John</hi> was ſent into all nations, but he came preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the doctrine of Baptiſme, and repentance in the Wilderneſſe of <hi>Iudea,</hi> and to the people of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but he who was to encreaſe, was found by <hi>Iohns</hi> Diſciples, then they left <hi>John</hi> and followed Jeſus, and ſaid they had found him whom <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets wrote of, Jeſus of <hi>Nazereth</hi> the Son of <hi>Ioſeph, Iohn</hi> 1.37.41.45 And herein did the friend of the Bride-groom rejoyce, even when he heard of the encreaſe of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>But Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. came and ſpake unto his Diſciples, ſaying, all power is given unto me in Heaven, and in earth; Go ye therefore and teach all Nations, Baptiſing them in the Name of the Father, Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you, and lo I am with you alwayes, even unto the end of the World.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, You ſay the commiſſion muſt needs be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and not the Spirit, becauſe it was onely the work of Chriſt, and not the Apoſtles work, to adminiſter the Holy Ghoſt, and <hi>Iohn Goſnel</hi> in the ſecond page of his book, doth conclude that the Baptiſme here inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, is with water, for the Baptiſme of the ſpirit, ſaith he was never adminiſtred by man, but Chriſt was the Miniſter of it himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I ſay, read the words of the commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on again, and there you ſhall find that Chriſt doth commiſſion them to Baptize in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and not into the water.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And yet ſo blind are ye, as to ſay this was not the Apoſtles work, neither was it in mans power ſay you, to adminiſter the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I ſay, Chriſt did nothing of himſelf, and all power which he had, was of the Father, and removed from the Father, verſ. the 18th. And greater works then theſe ſhall ye do, becauſe I go to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107205:18"/>ſaith Chriſt, and read, <hi>Acts.</hi> 8. and there you ſhall find, that the Apoſtles, verſ. 17, 18. were the onely adminiſtrators of the Holy Ghoſt, not by any power of their own, but by the power which Chriſt received of his Father, and gave unto them: Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt, read <hi>Acts.</hi> 19.6. when <hi>Paul</hi> had laid his hands upon them, the Holy Ghoſt came upon them; And you do not read in all the Scriptures, that Chriſt did thus act: But he made his Apoſtles the adminiſtrators thereof, and <hi>Iohn Goſnel</hi> in his 41 page ſaith thus; That the Baptiſm of the ſpirit is expreſſed, by the pouring forth of the ſpirit both in the Old and New Teſtament; and that he confeſſeth, is upon all his ſons and daughters, and upon all fleſh, and he proves this <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.28, 29. And yet before in his Book, ſaith, the Baptiſm of the Spirit, fell onely on ſome few at the firſt; but <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that both Jew and Greek, Bond and Free, were all Baptized by one Spirit into one Body, and were all made to drink into one Spirit; and thus it fals upon thee that which thou art charging upon ſome others, <hi>Eſa</hi> 24. They have tranſgreſſed the Law, and changed the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; which I ſay is Everlaſting, and a ſtorng Tower to his people, and the Saviour and Tried-ſtone to all that truſt in him; and in ſtead thereof ye have ſet up that unſtable water, and a carnal Ordinance of your own invention, and divers waſhings, which all muſt periſh in the uſing, after the commandments and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of men, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, You ſay that the Bible, on the Letter is the Judge of the Spirits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I ſay, you who have loſt the Spirit of the Lord, and know not Chriſt, to whom all Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is committed: muſt needs erre in Judgement, and ſtumble in viſion, and put light for darkneſs, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for light; and ſet up a carnal thing in ſtead of the inviſible and unchangeable God, and ſo by the Spirit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107205:19"/>of the Lord God, you who are for Judgement are Judged; and by that which you ſay is your Rule and Judge, are Condemned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1, 4. and <hi>John</hi> 5.22.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, You ſay, that the Letter is the Sword of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You who have loſt the Word of the Lord, and the Light of the Lord which is the Armour of God, know not the Sword of Spirit which is the Word of God, which is quick and powerful, and ſharper then any two edged ſword, and preceedeth out of the mouth of the Lamb, <hi>Kev.</hi> 19.15.<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, You ſay, that the Letter was the onely weapon wherewith Chriſt fought, and overcame the Devil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You who have loſt the Spirit of the Lord, know no other but a carnal weapon to fight with; but the Saints who are guided by the Spirit of the Lord, ſaid, that theirs were not carnal, but Spiritual, and mighty through the power of God to the pulling down of every high thought, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. And they ſaid, they were not Miniſters of the Letter, but of the Spirit, and that is the Reaſon of all your haling and pulling, of all your lies and ſlanders which ye are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to uſe, to defend your form; but know not the Armour of God, nor the ſword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God to defend you and overcome withal, <hi>Epeſ.</hi> 6.11, 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, You ſay, the Letter is the Law, the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and the Light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All this is contrary to the Scriptures, which you ſay, is your guide; for they ſay, Chriſt is the true Light that lighteth every man that cometh into the World, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>John</hi> 8.12. And thy Law is Light, ſayes <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 6.23. And the Teſtimony of Jeſus is the Spirit of Prophecy, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, You ſay, it was not the work of Chriſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107205:19"/>or his Apoſtles, to turn any to the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Read the Scripture, which ye ſo condemn us for denying, and ye may ſee that ye are they which deny them, and not we, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4, 6. where you may read; that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, I was ſent to turn them from the darkneſs to light, from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan unto God; and told them, that the light which did ſhine in their hearts, muſt give them the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, That the Bible is the Living Word of God, and able to make a man Wiſe unto Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I ſay, All that are in their ſins as ye are, know not Chriſt the living Word; and to me it is not a wonder to hear you call that living which is dead, and cannot give life nor power over ſin; but the Scripture doth affirm that Chriſt is the Word, and that it is he that ever liveth, and is made a high Prieſt by the power of a life that hath no end; and this is he that liveth and abideth for ever, read <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.9, 16. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.22.</p>
            <p>Thirteenthly, You ſay, that it is falſe doctrine to ſay, that he that is born of God ſinneth not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To you which know not the living and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Word, it is, and alwayes was, by ſuch, and to ſuch, as you are, who are Reprobates concerning the Faith which ſhould purifie you; but to the Children of the Lord this was never falſe doctrine, for they ſaid, he that was born of God ſinneth not, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.6, 10.</p>
            <p>Fourteenthly, Yon ſay, that the Bible is the Goſpel, and the power of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I ſay, Chriſt was the power of God, and Wiſdom of God, and the Rock of all his people in all ages, and the Foundation of the Prophets, and Apoſtles; and to us he is the ſame as he was to them in all ages, even the power of God to Salvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:107205:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And ſo all that are honeſt hearted among you, when you have read the Teachers Principles, may ſee I have not wronged you in ſaying, ye have ſet up ſhadowes above the ſubſtance, and the Letter above Chriſt, that gives Life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>From him who is in ſcorn cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Quaker.</hi> H. W.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 7. line 1. for them, read you. p. 13. l, 36. for love, r. low.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107205:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
